So here is a value iteration theorem can read
all of it I apologize I go t down the burden
handwriting series dignity rates at which
this condition in three is met for all N greater
than capital in okay so ? defined by step
four is ? optimal and VN + 1- V * is less
than or equal to ?/ 2 when 3 holds so when
this holds VN + 1 is ?x to close to be * right
so what is it A and B of kind of easy we already
seen that A and B as essentially Brouwer’s
fixed point theorem right.
I am sorry yeah the Brouwer’s fixed point
theorem gives us A and B correct what is the
difference between C&D why do I have two of
these things so they look contradict they
look contradictory not order it Reaper safe
but we did not anyone gives me the right answer
I will give you a bonus mark that essentially
which have been following whatever I have
been saying so far so further we will have
to take down the roll number and note down
that now I got their attention two people
who do not know the class averages for my
wishes tend to be in like 2 or 3 out of 20
or 50 it does not matter what the denominator
is does not seemed to change but so every
mark matters so tell me what is the difference
why do I need C and D sorry this ? optimal
means it is so maybe she phase say it in a
different way then you will get it so what
I am saying is that B p - v * is less than
? here I am saying BN + 1 - V * is less than
? / 2.
Remember my space V does not necessarily contain
only value functions it is just a space of
functions right VN + 1 need not be the value
function corresponding to the policy p even
though I recover p by being greedy with respect
to VN + 1 does not mean if I actually solve
for value of p if I find Vp it need not be
VN + 1 right so what three is telling me is
that v p is ? not what C is telling me is
v p epsilon optimal what D is telling me is
that v+ 1 is ? / 2 optimal okay so fun let
me give you the work how about you enough
I never offered them before right.
This is this is on offer nobody took it that
is easy enough right all you need to do is
just mean following the multiple times I kept
saying that V is not the space of value function
is the very beginning when somebody said V
is a space of value function I corrected you
of this class very beginning of this class
anyway so let us look at the proof well A
and B are immediate the follower Brouwer’s
fixed point theorem so we will start off with
C and D right
so just assume that 3 is made for some n okay
so n it is already met that condition has
been met right and that we p the p has been
derived from doing this the p has been derived
from doing this.
And now I can use my triangle inequality right
it does not matter that then this actually
does not matter right whether these conditions
are met or not I can take an arbitrary vp
and a V * and I can use a triangle inequality
and write this because it is just about three
points in space right we talked about how
I can keep using the triangle inequality in
an arbitrary fashion because all I am talking
about are just some 3 points in space it so
happens that one of them is v p other one
is VN + 1 the third one is v * but this will
hold regardless of which three points I pick
okay.
So here is a tricky thing I want you to look
at
so let us look at L p say I want L p to act
on VN + 1 right I want Lp to act on BN + 1
right so what will be L p acting on Vn + 1
is it space of what l p is a an operator corresponding
to the bellman equation for ? right sort of
way I said last class we left off by saying
l p is a contraction so that L p so L p is
just a bellman value equation operating on
VN + 1 so what would that be will be this
right this but instead of R max here I will
have a summation over p Sa say allow summation
over p Sa but what I have done here by p itself
is an R max a right just one action.
So if you remember I told you about the deterministic
policy is right so this whole thing will go
I will just replace this with p S is this
will be expected value of R given S, p S probability
of s’ given s come up is VN + 1’ so that
will essentially be the L p acting on VN+
1 right is it clear this is L p on VN + 1
I just read it out I just write in unit known
as mnemonic expected value of R given s, ps
+ ? times summation over s’ probability
of s’ given p s x VN + 1 s’ okay so now
thing that you have to notice how would I
get to this ps is by using max I use the max
operator over this right.
So if I had done L on VN + 1 what would I
have obtained L on VN + 1 is essentially this
right next right this is this is what this
one L or VN + 1 is essentially this right
so what I have done here because I chose my
p to be the max action here so whether I apply
L p on VN + 1 or whether I apply L on VN +
1 it is the same because the p was chosen
to be the max action right so I can say that
this is equal to sorry not equivalent so the
two are equal
that makes it easier.
.
Now we are going to start simplifying stuff.
So I am going to take this expression I am
going to try and simplify that okay we can
I can replace v p with L p v p dot ypp is
a fixed point nothing will change I can just
replace it to the LP vp now so can I do this
same application of the triangle inequality
as we had before so three points are Lp v
/ vn+ 1 and L VN + 1 so L VN + 1 is just another
point in space between three points I can
write this triangle inequality so this is
less than or equal to H this is equal to
right so this is the reduction we talked about
here so from LV I went to L p LVL + 1 I cent
L p VN + 1 and from VN + 1 I went to LVN because
that is how VN + 1 was generated by applying
L on VL okay so I have written that.
.
Now I can simplify this
so I have ep n + 1 here vp -VN + 1 here sorry
and v p - VN+ 1 here so I can take it to that
side simplify things so I will just get okay
that is just the first term now we have to
simplify the second term towards the second
term.
.
I just like we did earlier I have done a repeated
application of the triangle inequality is
only tricky thing here is a summation goes
to infinity because only when I repeat this
till infinity will go to B* right but that
is fine because this is anyway it is a vanishing
quantity as we go along right so this of this
sum will actually okay exist limit of a summation
yeah well I am you can think of this as V
* - VN+ 1 right because I am just talking
about the norm right so as v*- VN + 1 and
then I have written this up okay.
So this is VN + 1 that is VN + 2 then Vn +
2 VN + 3 blah this one so forth so what will
this be you only said it to be a limit of
a summation right guys I need to take 1 ? out
okay so what do we have so we have the first
component is less than equal to ?x1 – ? x
VN + 1 – VN right but when three holes what
is VN+ 1 - VF ? x 1 minus ?/ 2 ? right so
if I plug that then what will I get ?/2 to
plug it in there what will I get ? / two so
I have few components here so vp - v * is
less than or equal to ?x 2 + ?x 2 which is
? right v p - v * is less than or equal to
okay when we have actually to complete the
proof we have to do that but I am asking you
to do that what was the other thing that we
wanted to show D or later right.
So D essentially was to show that VN + 1will
be at least ?x to close so we already done
so we substitute that here so we get ?/ 2
so is that so VN - p.m. sorry VN + 1 - v*
is less than or equal to ?/2 and what we are
showing there is v p - v * is less than or
equal to ? like so that is basically done
so we have shown this theorem so essentially
what we have here is that value iteration
converges with that stopping criterion it
converges to a ? optimal policy so you have
to pick an ? first remember ? comes as part
of the problem definition.
So once you pick an ? you can find a stopping
criterion using that expression there and
you are all set okay so there is one other
very interesting thing that people talk about
from a theoretical analysis of algorithms
for solving these kinds of MDPs right so it
is called the rate of convergence so I have
shown you that it converges so there is a
whole concept called rate of convergence right
how quickly does it approached right so I
am not going to get into a huge discussions
on rate of convergence and like I mentioned
with the deterministic policy thing I actually
put up a small right upon rate of convergence
as well you can read it.
One thing which I want to tell you is that
so you can with a little bit of not much right
so L is a contraction mapping L is a contraction
so at every iteration right so my
so what is the contraction factor for L we
did this ? right so for every iteration I
can show that my iterates that is basically
I start off with v0 then I become take me
one then V2 V3 and so on so forth every iteration
I can so that the successive iterates will
become ? closer to v* right.
So I have some so v1 was some x close to v
* then v2 will be ? X closer to so ? is small
it will converge faster if ? is very large
it will converse lower right so this is called
linear convergence with the rate of ? right
so if it falls as ?2 then it will be quadratic
convergence right so but linear convergence
with the rate of ? so this is essentially
the thing so the interesting aspects I mean
if you want to get into the more into the
theory of all of these things is to start
studying the rates of convergence of different
algorithms and so on so forth which I am not
going to get into but there is something for
as an aside so that you can look at it.